Guide to the Earl Ivan Brown Papers, circa 1900-1936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Earl Ivan Brown papers circa 1900-1936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Brown, Earl Ivan, 1874-1963.
1.0 Linear Feet 500 Items
Earl Ivan Brown, civil engineer with the United States Army Corps of Engineers; served in Philippines and Cuba during the Spanish-American War; 92nd Division Engineer in the American Expeditionary Forces; developed river and harbor improvements in the United States, principally on the Atlantic and Gulf coasts and on the Ohio River, including the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal.
Collection includes correspondence, genealogical materials, notebooks, legal papers, and other collected papers of Earl Ivan Brown, a civil engineer with the Army Corps of Engineers, 1900s-1930s. Materials document Brown's career developing river and harbor improvements on the Atlantic and Gulf Coasts as well as his work on the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Earl Ivan Brown Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift.
Biographical Note
Earl Ivan Brown, civil engineer, was born at County Line, Georgia, on 13 October 1874 and graduated 6th in his class from the United States Military Academy in 1898. As a member of the Corps of Engineers, Brown served in both the Philippines and Cuba during and after the Spanish-American War. He participated in the Philippine Insurrection and the Moro Expedition before traveling to the Caribbean for the Cuban Pacification in 1906. During World War I, Brown was the 92nd Division Engineer in the American Expeditionary Forces. Throughout his career Brown developed river and harbor improvements in the United States. He worked principally on the Atlantic and Gulf coasts and on the Ohio River. Brown also worked on the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal and finished his career in 1938 as the Division Engineer of the South Atlantic Division.
Colonel Earl I. Brown died on 25 June 1963 in Durham, North Carolina at age 88. He is buried in Arlington National Cemetery. Brown was the son of William F. and Emily Absilla (Hagen) Brown. He was married to Annie Thompson who died in 1953, and then to Marylily Fisher. His nephew, Earl Ivan Brown, II, was a professor of Civil Engineering at Duke University from 1960 to 1982.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, genealogical materials, notebooks, legal papers, and other collected papers of Earl Ivan Brown, civil engineer with the Army Corps of Engineers. Materials document Brown's career developing river and harbor improvements on the Atlantic and Gulf Coasts as well as his work on the Chesapeake and Delaware Canal.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Brown, Earl Ivan, 1874-1963
Chesapeake and Delaware Canal (Del. and Md.) -- History
Civil engineers -- United States
United States. Army. Corps of Engineers. South Atlantic Division
Contents of Collection
- Earl Ivan Brown Papers, circa 1900-1936, (3 boxes)
  Materials have not been arranged or described beyond their original condition.
  - Letters and Memoranda, etc. (Box 1)
  - Genealogy
  - Legal Papers (folder and roll)
  - Letters, 1918 June 11-Dec. 5 (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1919 Jan. 2-May 19
  - Various Papers
  - Chesapeake and Delaware Canal
  - Various Papers (Box 3)
  - Clippings, etc.
  - "Application of the Theory of Col. E. I. Brown for Flow in Tidal Canals and Estuaries," Thesis of R.R. Arnold, May, 1936
  - Passport
  - Pocket Notebook, 1901
  - Book of Family Marriages, Births, and Deaths
  - Ledger